Chapter 135, The Chase, Third Day.
The morning of the third day dawned fair and fresh, and once more the solitary
night man of the four mast head was relieved by crowds of the daylight
lookouts who dotted every mast and almost every spar.
Do you see him? cried Ahab, but the whale was not yet in sight. In his
infallible wake, though, but follow that wake, that's all. Helm there, steady as
thou goest, and hast been going. What a lovely day again. Were it a new made
world and made for a summer house to the angels, and this morning the first of
its throwing open to them, a fairer day could not dawn upon that world. Here's
food for thought. Had Ahab time to think. But Ahab and never thinks, he
only feels, feels, feels. That's tingling enough for mortal man. To think's audacity.
God only has that right and privilege.
Thinking is or ought to be a coolness and a calmness, and our poor hearts
throb, and our poor brains beat too much for that. And yet I've sometimes thought
my brain was very calm, frozen calm.
This old skull cracks so like a glass in which the contents turn to ice and
shiver it. And still this hair is growing now, this moment growing. And
heat must breed it. But no, it's like that sword of common grass that will
grow anywhere between the earthly cliffs of Greenland ice or in Vuvius's lava.
How the wild winds blow it. They whip it about me as the torn shreds of split
sails lash the tossed ship they cling to. A vile wind that has no doubt blown
air this through prison corridors and cells and wards of hospitals and
ventilated them and now comes blowing hither as innocent as fleeces. Out upon
it it's tainted. Were I the wind, I'd blow no more on such a wicked, miserable
world. I'd crawl somewhere to a cave and slink there. And yet is a noble and
heroic thing the wind. Whoever conquered it, in every fight, it has the last and
bitterest blow. Run tilting at it, and you but run through it. Ha! A coward
wind that strikes stark naked men, but will not stand to receive a single blow.
Even Ahab is a braver thing, a nobler thing than that. Would now the wind but
had a body. But all the things that most exasperate and outrage mortal man, all
these things are bodyless, but only bodily as objects, not as agents.
There's a most special, a most cunning, oh, a most malicious difference. And yet
I say again, and swear it now, that there's something all glorious and
gracious in the wind. These warm trade winds at least that in the clear heavens
blow straight on in strong and steadfast vigorous mildness and veer not from
their mark however the baser currents of the sea may turn and tack and mightiest
Mississippi of the land swift and swerve about uncertain where to go at last and
by the eternal poles. These same trades that so directly blow my good ship on.
These trades are something like them.
Something so unchangeable and full as strong. Blow my keeled soul along.
To it a loft there. What do you see?
Nothing, sir. Nothing. And noon at hand.
The deloon goes a begging. See the sun.
I I it must be so. I've oversailed him.
How got the start. I. He's chasing me now, not I. Him. That's bad. I might
have known it, too. Fool. The lines. The harpoons. He's towing. I I have run by
him last night. About about Come down all of you, but the regular lookouts.
Man the braces.
Steering as she had done, the wind had been somewhat on the Peekquad's quarter,
so that now being pointed in the reverse direction, the braced ship sailed hard
upon the breeze as she rechurned the cream in her own white wake. Against the
wind he now steers for the open jaw, murmured Starbucks to himself, as he
coiled the new hauled manrace upon the rail. God keep us. But already my bones
feel damp within me and from the inside wet my flesh. I misdoubt me that I
disobey my God in obeying him.
Stand by to sway me up, cried Ahab, advancing to the hemp and basket. We
should meet him soon. I I sir, and straightway Starbucks did Ahab's
bidding, and once more Ahab swung on high. A whole hour now passed, gold
beaten out to ages. Time itself now held long breaths with keen surprise, but at
last some three points off the weather bow, Ahab described the spout again, and
instantly from the three mast heads, three shrieks went up as if the tongues
of fire had voiced it.
Forehead to forehead I meet thee this third time. Moby Dick on deck there.
Race sharper up. Crowd her into the wind's eye. He's too far off to lower
yet. Mr. Starbucks. The sails shake.
Stand over that helmsman with a top maul. So he travels fast and I must
down. But let me have one more good look round a loft here at the sea. There's
time for that. An old old sight and yet somehow so young. I and not changed a
wink since I first saw it. A boy from the sand hills of Nantucket. The same.
The same. The same to Noah as to me.
There's a soft shower to Lurard. Such lovely lurings. They must lead somewhere
to something else than common land more palmy than the palms. Lured. The white
whale goes that way. Look to Windward then. The better if the bitterer
quarter. But goodbye. Goodbye old mast head. What's this green? Ah, tiny mosses
in these warped cracks. No such green weather stains on Ahab's head. There's
the difference now between man's old age and matters. But I, old mast, we both
grow old together. Sound in our hulls, though. Or are we not my ship? I minus a
leg, that's all. By heaven, this dead wood has the better of my live flesh
every way. I can't compare with it. And I've known some ships made of dead trees
outlast the lives of men made of the most vital stuff of vital fathers.
What's that? He said, "He should still go before me, my pilot. And yet to be
seen again. But where? Well, I have eyes at the bottom of the sea, supposing I
descend those endless stairs, and all night I've been sailing from him,
wherever he did sink to. I like many more thou's dire truth as
touching thyself, O Parsy. But Ahab, there thy shot fell short. Goodbye, mast
head. Keep a good eye upon the whale while I'm gone. We'll talk tomorrow.
Nay, tonight when the white whale lies down there, tied by head and tail.
He gave the word, and still gazing around him, was steadily lowered through
the cloven blue air to the deck. In due time the boats were lowered, but as
standing in his shallop stern, Ahab just hovered upon the point of the descent,
he waved to the mate, who held one of the tackle ropes on deck, and bad him paws.
Starbucks.
Sir, for the third time, my soul ship starts upon this voyage. Starbucks,
I sir, thou wilt have it so. Some ships sail from their ports, and ever
afterwards are missing, Starbucks.
Truth, sir, sad as truth.
Some men die at eide, some at low water, some at the full of the flood. And I
feel now like a billow that's all one crested comb. Starbucks,
I am old. Shake hands with me, man.
Their hands met, their eyes fastened, and Starbucks tears the glue. Oh, my
captain. My captain, noble heart. Go not, go not. See, it's a brave man that
weeps. How great the agony of the persuasion. Then lower away, cried Ahab, tossing the
mate's arm from him. Stand by the crew.
In an instant, the boat was pulling round close under the stern.
The sharks, the sharks, cried a voice from the low cabin window. There, "Oh,
master, my master, come back." But Ahab heard nothing, for his own voice was
high lifted then, and the boat leaped on.
Yet the voice spake true, for scarcity he pushed from the ship when numbers of
sharks, seemingly rising from out the dark waters beneath the hull,
maliciously snapped at the blades of the oars every time they dipped in the
water, and in this way accompanied the boat with their bites. It is a thing not
uncommonly happening to the whaleboats in those swarming seas. the sharks at
times apparently following them in the same preient way that vultures hover
over the banners of marching regiments in the east. But these were the first
sharks that had been observed by the Peekquad since the white whale had first
been described. And whether it was that Ahab's crew were all such tiger yellow
barbarians, and therefore their flesh more musky to the senses of the sharks,
a matter sometimes well known to affect them. However it was, they seemed to
follow that one boat without molesting the others.
Heart of rot steel, murmured Starbucks, gazing over the side, and following with
his eye the receding boat. Can thou yet ring boldly to that sight, lowering thy
keel among ravening sharks, and followed by them open mouth to the chase? And
this the critical third day. For when three days flow together in one
continuous intense pursuit, be sure the first is the morning, the second the
noon, and the third the evening, and the end of that thing. Be that end what it
may. Oh my God. What is this that shoots through me and leaves me so deadly calm
yet expectant, fixed at the top of a shutter? Future things swim before me as
in empty outlines and skeletons. All the past is somehow grown dim.
Mary girl, thou fadest in pale glories behind me. Boy, I seem to see but thy
eyes grown wondrous blue. Strangest problems of life seem clearing, but
clouds sweep between. Is my journeys end coming? My legs feel faint like his who
has footed it all day. Feel thy heart.
Beats it yet? Stir thyself, Starbucks.
Stave it off. Move, move. Speak aloud.
Mast head there. See my boy's hand on the hill.
Crazed a loft there. Keep thy keenest eye on the boats. Mark well the whale. Ho
again. Drive off that hawk. See, he pecks. He tears the vein. Pointing to
the red flag flying at the main truck.
Huh? He soarses away with it. Where's the old man now? Seeest thou that side,
O Ahab? Shudder. Shudder.
The boats had not gone very far, when, by a signal from the mast heads, a
downward-pointed arm, Ahab knew that the whale had sounded, but intending to be
near him at the next rising, he held on his way a little sideways from the
vessel, the barmed crew maintaining the profoundest silence as the headbeat
waves hammered and hammered against the opposing bow.
Drive, drive in your nails, oh ye waves, to their uttermost heads. drive them in.
You but strike a thing without a lid, and no coffin and no hearse can be mine,
and hemp only can kill me. Ha ha.
Suddenly, the waters around them slowly swelled in broad circles, then quickly
upheaved, as if sideways, sliding from a submerged berg of ice, swiftly rising to
the surface. A low rumbling sound was heard, a subterraneanous hum, and then
all held their breaths as bedraggled with trailing ropes and harpoons and
lances, a vast form shot lengthwise, but obliquely from the sea. Shrouded in a
thin, drooping veil of mist, it hovered for a moment in the rainbowed air, and
then fell swamping back into the deep.
crushed 30 feet upwards, the waters flashed for an instant like heaps of
fountains, then brokenly sank in a shower of flakes, leaving the circling
surface creamed like new milk round the marble trunk of the whale. "Give way,"
cried Ahab to the orars, and the boats darted forward to the attack. But
maddened by yesterday's fresh irons that corroded in him, Moby Dick seemed
combinedly possessed by all the angels that fell from heaven. The wide tears of
welded tendons overspreading his broad white forehead beneath the transparent
skin looked knitted together as head-on he came churning his tail among the
boats and once more flailed them apart spilling out the irons and lances from
the two mates boats and dashing in one side of the upper part of their boughs
but leaving Ahabs almost without a scar while Dagu and Quequ were stopping the
strained planks and as the whale swimming out from them turned and showed
one entire flank as he shot by them again. At that moment a quick cry went
up, lashed round and round to the fish's back, pinioned in the turns upon turns
in which during the past night the whale had reeled the involutions of the lines
around him. The half-to body of the parsey was seen, his sable raignment
frayed to shreds, his distended eyes turned full upon old Ahab.
The harpoon dropped from his hand.
Be fooled. Be fooled. Drawing in a long, lean breath, I parsy, I see thee again.
I and thou goest before. And this this then is the hearse that thou dst
promise. But I hold thee to the last letter of thy word. Where is the second
hearse? Away mates to the ship. Those boats are useless now. Repair them if
you can in time and return to me. If not, Ahab is enough to die. Down men.
The first thing but offers to jump from this boat I stand in. That thing I
harpoon ye are not other men but my arms and legs and so obey me. Where's the
whale gone down again?
But he looked too nigh the boat, for as if bent upon escaping with the corpse he
bore, and as if the particular place of the last encounter had been a stage in
his lured voyage, Moby Dick was now again steadily swimming forward, and had
almost passed the ship, which thus far had been sailing in the contrary
direction to him, though for the present her headway had been stopped. He seemed
swimming with his utmost velocity, and now only intent upon pursuing his own
straight path in the sea. "Oh, Ahab!"
cried Starbucks, "not too late, is it, even now, the third day, to desist. See,
Moby Dick seeks thee not. It is thou, thou that madly seekest him." setting
sail to the rising wind, the lonely boat was swiftly impelled to lured by both
oars and canvas. And at last, when Ahab was sliding by the vessel, so near as to
plainly distinguish Starbucks face as he leaned over the rail, he hailed him to
turn the vessel about and follow him, not too swiftly, at a judicious
interval. Glancing upward he saw Tashego Quiqu and Dagu eagerly mounting to the
three mast heads while the oresman were rocking in the two staved boats which
had but just been hoisted to the side and were busily at work in repairing
them one after the other through the port holes as he sped. He also caught
flying glimpses of stub and flask busying themselves on deck among bundles
of new irons and lances. As he saw all this, as he heard the hammers in the
broken boats, far other hammers seemed driving a nail into his heart. But he
rallied, and now marking that the vein or flag was gone from the main mast
head, he shouted to Tashego, who had just gained that perch, to descend again
for another flag, and a hammer and nails, and so nail it to the mast.
whether by the three days running chase and the resistance to his swimming
in the nodded hamper he bore, or whether it was some latent deceitfulness and
malice in him. Whichever was true, the white whale's way now began to abate, as
it seemed, from the boat so rapidly nearing him once more, though indeed the
whale's last start had not been so long a one as before. And still, as Ahab
glided over the waves, the unpittying sharks accompanied him, and so
perttonaciously stuck to the boat, and so continually bit at the pllying oars,
that the blades became jagged and crunched, and left small splinters in
the sea at almost every dip.
Heed them not, those teeth but give new rollocks to your oars. Pull on. It is
the better rest, the shark's jaw, than the yielding water. But at every bite,
sir, the thin blades grow smaller and smaller. They will last long enough.
Pull on. But who can tell? He muttered, whether these sharks swim to feast on
the whale or on Ahab. But pull on. I all alive. Now we near him. The helm. Take
the helm. Let me pass. And so saying, two of the oresmen helped him forward to
the boughs of the still flying boat.
At length, as the craft was cast to one side, and ran ranging along with the
white whale's flank, he seemed strangely oblivious of its advance, as the whale
sometimes will, and Ahab was fairly within the smoky mountain mist, which
thrown off from the whale's spout, curled round his great Manadnuk hump. He
was even thus close to him when his body arched back and both arms lengthwise
high lifted to the poise. He darted his fierce iron and his far fiercer curse
into the hated whale. As both steel and curse sank into the socket, as if sucked
into a morass, Moby Dick's sideways wythe, spasmodically rolled his NY flank
against the bow, and without staving a hole in it, so suddenly caned the boat
over that had it not been for the elevated part of the gunnel to which he
then clung, Ahab would once more have been tossed into the sea, as it was,
three of the oresmen, who forneew not the precise instant of the dart, and
were therefore unprepared for its effects. These were flung out, but so
fell that in an instant two of them clutched the gunnel again, and rising to
its level on a combing wave, hurled themselves bodily inboard again, the
third man helplessly dropping a stern, but still afloat and swimming.
Almost simultaneously, with a mighty volition of ungraduated, instantaneous
swiftness, the white whale darted through the weltering sea. But when Ahab
cried out to the steersmen to take new turns with the line and hold it so, and
commanded the crew to turn round on their seats, and tow the boat up to the
mark. The moment the treacherous line felt that double strain and tug, it
snapped in the empty air. What breaks in me? Some senue cracks.
It is whole again. Oars burst in upon him.
Hearing the tremendous rush of the sea crashing boat, the whale wheeled round
to present his blank forehead at bay.
But in that evolution, catching sight of the nearing black hull of the ship,
seemingly seeing in it the source of all his persecutions, bethinking it, it may
be a larger and nobler foe. Of a sudden he bore down upon its advancing prow,
smiting his jaws amid fiery showers of foam.
Ahab staggered. His hands smoke his forehead. I grow blind. Hands stretch
out before me that I may yet grope my way. Is it night?
The whale, the ship, cried the cringing oarsman. Oars, oars, slope downward to
thy depths, O sea, that air it be forever too late. Ahab may slide this
last last time upon his mark. I see the ship, the ship. Bash on my men. Will you
not save my ship?
But as the oresman violently forced their boat through the sledgehammering
seas, the before whales smitten bowends of two planks burst through, and in an
instant almost, the temporarily disabled boat lay nearly level with the waves,
its halfwading, splashing crew trying hard to stop the gap and bail out the pouring water.
Meanwhile, for that one beholding instant, Tashego's mast head hammer
remained suspended in his hand, and the red flag halfwrapping him as with a
plaid then streamed itself straight out from him, as his own forward flowing
heart, while Starbucks and Stub, standing upon the bow sprit beneath,
caught sight of the downcoming monster just as soon as he The whale. The whale uphelm uphelm. Oh
all ye sweet powers of air. Now hug me close. Let not Starbucks die if die he
must in a woman's fainting fit. Uphelm.
I say you fools. The jaw. The jaw. Is this the end of all my bursting prayers?
All my lifelong fidelities. Oh Ahab.
Ahab. Lo thy work. Steady helmsman.
Steady. Nay nay. uphelm again. He turns to meet us. Oh, his unappeasable brow
drives on toward one whose duty tells him he cannot depart. My God, stand by me now.
Stand not by me, but stand under me.
Whoever you are that will now help Stub, for Stub, too sticks here. I grin at
thee, thou grinning whale. Whoever helped Stub or kept Stub awake but
Stub's own unwinking eye. And now poor stub goes to bed upon a mattress that is
all too soft. Would it were stuffed with brushwood? I grin at thee, thou grinning
whale. Look ye sun, moon, and stars. I call ye assassins of as good a fellow as
ever spouted up his ghost. For all that I would yet ring glasses with ye, would
you but hand the cup? Oh, oh, oh, oh, thou grinning whale. But there'll be
plenty of gulping soon. Why fly you not, oh Ahab, for me? Off shoes and jacket to
it. Let Stub die in his drawers. A most moldy and overs salted death, though.
Cherries, cherries, cherries. Oh, flask for one red cherry. Air we die.
Cherries. I only wish that we were where they grow. Oh, stub. I hope my poor
mother's drawn my part pay this. If not, few coppers will now come to her, for
the voyage is up. From the ship's boughs, nearly all the seamen now hung
inactive, hammers, bits of plank, lances, and harpoons mechanically
retained in their hands, just as they had darted from their various
employments, all their enchanted eyes intent upon the whale, which from side
to side, strangely vibrating his predestinating head, sent a broad band
of overspreading semic-ircular foam before him as he rushed. retribution,
swift vengeance, eternal malice were in his whole aspect, and in spite of all
that mortal man could do, the solid white buttress of his forehead smoked
the ship's starboard bow, till men and timbers reeled. Some fell flat upon
their faces. Like dislodged trucks, the heads of the harpooners aloft shook on
their bull-like necks. Through the breach they heard the waters pour as
mountain torrent down a flume.
"The ship, the hearse, the second hearse!" cried Ahab from the boat. Its
wood could only be American.
Diving beneath the settling ship, the whale ran quivering along its keel. But
turning underwater, swiftly shot to the surface again, far off the other bow,
but within a few yards of Ahab's boat, where for a time he lay quietiescent,
I turn my body from the sun. What ho, Tashego, let me hear thy hammer. Oh ye
three unsurrendered spires of mine. Thou uncracked keel and only god bullied
hull. Thou firm deck andaughty helm and polepointed prowl. Death glorious ship
must ye then perish. And without me am I cut off from the last fond pride of
meanest shipwrecked captains. Oh lonely death on lonely life. Oh, now I feel my
topmost greatness lies in my topmost grief.
Ho ho, from all your furthest bounds, pour you now in, you bold billows of my
whole foregone life, and top this one piled comr of my death.
Towards thee I roll thou all destroying but unconquering whale. To the last I
grapple with thee. From hell's heart I stab at thee. For hate's sake I spit my
last breath at thee. Sink all coffins and all hurses to one common pool. And
since neither can be mine, let me then tow to pieces while still chasing thee,
though tied to thee thou damned whale.
Thus I give up the spear.
The harpoon was darted. The stricken whale flew forward with igniting
velocity. The line ran through the grooves, ran foul. Ahab stooped to clear
it. He did clear it, but the flying turn caught him round the neck and
voicelessly as Turkish mutes bowring their victim. He was shot out of the
boat. Air the crew knew he was gone.
Next instant, the heavy eye splice in the rope's final end flew out of the
stark empty tub knocked down an orsman and smiting the sea, disappeared in its depths.
For an instant the tranced boat's crew stood still, then turned. The ship.
Great God, where is the ship? Soon they through dim bewildering mediums saw her
sidelong fading phantom as in the gaseous Fatam Morgana only the uppermost
mass out of the water. While fixed by infatuation or fidelity or fate to their
once lofty perches, the pagan harpineers still maintain their sinking lookouts on
the sea. And now concentric circle seized the lone boat itself and all the
crew and each floating ore and every lance pole and spinning animate and
inanimate all round and round in one vortex carried the smallest chip of the
peekquad out of sight.
But as the last Wellmings intermixingly poured themselves over the sunken head
of the Indian at the main mast, leaving a few inches of the erect spar yet
visible, together with long streaming yards of the flag, which calmly
undulated with ironical coincidings over the destroying billows they almost
touched. At that instant, a red arm and a hammer hovered backwardly uplifted in
the open air in the act of nailing the flag faster and yet faster to the
subsiding spar. a skyhawk that tauntingly had followed the main truck
downwards from its natural home among the stars, pecking at the flag, and in
commoting Tashego there, this bird now chanced to intercept its broad
fluttering wing between the hammer and the wood, and simultaneously feeling
that ethereal thrill, the submerged savage beneath, in his death grasp, kept
his hammer frozen there. And so the bird of heaven with archangelic shrieks and
his imperial beak thrust upward and his whole captive form folded in the flag of
Ahab went down with his ship which like Satan would not sink to hell till she
had dragged a living part of heaven along with her and helmeted herself with it.
Now small fowls flew screaming over the yet yawning gulp. A sullen white surf
beat against its steep sides. Then all collapsed, and the great shroud of the
sea rolled on as it rolled 5,000 years ago